"Plant-Based Protein: Are Pea
and Soy Protein Isolates Harmful?"
So, are these plant-based
burgers healthy or not?
And the answer is…
compared to what?
Eating is kind of a zero-sum game;
every food has an opportunity cost.
I mean, every time we
put something in our mouth
it’s a lost opportunity to put
something even healthier in our mouth.
So, if you want to know
if something is healthy,
you have to compare it to
what you’d be eating instead.
So, for example,
are eggs healthy?
Compared to a breakfast
link sausage? Yes!
But compared to oatmeal?
Not even close.
But look, sausage is considered
a group 1 carcinogen.
In other words, we know consumption
of processed meat causes cancer.
Each 50-gram serving a day,
that’s a single breakfast link,
was linked to an 18% higher
risk of colorectal cancer.
So, the risk of getting colorectal
cancer eating one link a day
is about the same as the increased
risk of lung cancer you’d get
breathing secondhand smoke all
day living with a smoking spouse.
So, compared to sausage,
eggs are healthy,
but compared to oatmeal,
eggs are not.
So, when it comes to Beyond Meat
and Impossible Burger,
yeah, they may be better in
that they have less saturated fat,
but, hey, you want
less saturated fat?
Plant-based meat
alternatives are no match
for unprocessed plant foods,
such as beans or lentils.
And a bean burrito or lentil
soup could certainly fill
the same culinary niche
as a lunchtime burger.
But if you are going to
have some kind of burger,
it’s easy to argue that the
plant-based versions are healthier.
There is a sodium issue, and
it’s not that much, if any, lower,
in saturated fat, since
they use coconut oil,
which is basically just
as bad as animal fat;
there’s not much
advantage on that front.
Though the total protein is
similar across the board,
does this matter? Or Is there any
advantage to eating plant protein
over animal protein?
Let’s look at the association
between animal and plant
protein intake and mortality.
In the twin Harvard cohorts,
following more than 100,000 men
and women over decades, “…after
adjusting for other dietary
and lifestyle factors, animal
protein intake was associated
with a higher risk [of] mortality,
particularly [dying from
cardiovascular disease], whereas
higher plant protein intake
was associated with
[a] lower all-cause mortality”,
meaning a lower risk of dying
from all causes put together.
So, “replacing animal protein
of various origins
with plant protein was associated
with lower mortality”,
especially if you’re replacing
processed meat and egg protein,
which were the worst. But when
it comes to living a longer life,
plant protein sources beat out
each and every animal protein source.
Not just better
than bacon and eggs,
but better than burgers, chicken,
turkey, fish, and dairy protein.
Together with other studies, these
“findings support the importance
of protein sources for the
long-term health outcome
and suggest plants constitute
a preferred protein source
compared [to] animal foods.” Why?
Well, unlike animal protein, plant
protein has not been associated
with increased levels
of the cancer-promoting
growth hormone IGF-1, for example.
Now, soy protein is similar
enough to animal protein
that at high enough doses, like eating
two Impossible Burgers a day,
you may bump your IGF-1.
But the only reason we care
about IGF-1 is cancer risk,
and if anything, higher soy
intake is associated with
a decreased risk of cancer.
For example, a recent systematic
review and meta-analysis found
that soy protein intake was
associated with a decreased risk
in breast cancer mortality;
we’re talking “a 12 percent reduction
in breast cancer death
[associated with] each 5-gram-a-day
increase in soy protein intake.”
But the high soy groups
in these studies
were on the order of
more than 16 grams a day,
associated with a
whopping 62% lower risk
of dying from breast cancer.
More than 10 grams of soy
protein a day may be good,
associated with cutting
breast cancer mortality risk
nearly in half, and getting
more than 16 grams a day
may be better, which is like
one Impossible Burger a day.
But we simply don’t know what happens
at consumption levels far above that.
Plant protein has also been
linked to lower blood pressure,
reduced LDL cholesterol, and
improved insulin sensitivity.
No wonder “substitution of
plant protein for animal protein
has been related to a lower incidence
of cardiovascular disease
and type 2 diabetes.”
Indeed, 21 different studies following
nearly a half million people,
and “high… animal protein
intakes [were] associated with
an increased risk of [type 2 diabetes],
whereas [even just] moderate
plant protein intake
is associated with a decreased
risk of [type 2 diabetes].”
OK, but these were just
observational studies.
They all tried to control for other
dietary and lifestyle factors,
but you can’t prove cause-and-effect,
until...you put it to the test.
The “Effect of Replacing Animal
Protein with Plant Protein
on [blood sugar] Control in
Diabetes: A Systematic Review
and Meta-Analysis of
Randomized Controlled Trials.”
Even just switching out about
a third of your protein
from animal to plant sources
yielded significant improvements
in long-term blood sugar control,
and fasting blood sugars, and insulin.
You can do the same thing
looking at cholesterol.
Here’s a systematic review and
meta-analysis of randomized
controlled trials on the effect
of plant protein on blood fats.
And indeed, swapping in plant
protein for animal protein
decreases LDL cholesterol,
and this benefit occurs
whether you start out at high
cholesterol or low cholesterol,
whether you’re swapping out
dairy, or meat, and eggs,
and whether you’re swapping in
soy or other plant proteins.
We’ve known about the beneficial
effects of soy on cholesterol
going back nearly 40 years, but
other sources of plant protein
can do it as well. Yeah, but
we’re not swapping beans for beef.
These products are mostly
just isolated plant proteins,
mostly pea protein isolate
in the case of Beyond,
and concentrated soy protein
in the case of Impossible.
If you just isolate out
the plant proteins themselves
are you still going to get benefits?
Yes, surprisingly. Check it out.
Interestingly, the researchers
concluded, that they did not ﬁnd
a signiﬁcant difference between
protein isolate products
and whole food sources, “suggesting
that the cholesterol-lowering
effects are at least, in part, attributable
to the plant protein
itself rather than just
the associated nutrients.”
So, it’s not just because
plant protein travels
with fiber or less saturated fat.
Plant proteins break down
into a different distribution
of amino acids; and so, it’s
like if you give people arginine,
an amino acid found
more in plant foods,
that alone can bring
down people’s cholesterol.
And even plant protein concentrates
used in these products
aren’t pure protein, retaining
a few active compounds
such as phytosterols and antioxidants,
which also can have beneficial effects.